<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://leonardmutambanengwe.github.io/leonardblog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://leonardmutambanengwe.github.io/leonardblog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-01-06T07:17:20-06:00</updated><id>https://leonardmutambanengwe.github.io/leonardblog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Leonard Mutambanengwe</title><subtitle>An easy to use blogging platform with support for Jupyter Notebooks.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Filling the void</title><link href="https://leonardmutambanengwe.github.io/leonardblog/2021/01/14/Filling-the-void.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Filling the void" /><published>2021-01-14T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-14T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://leonardmutambanengwe.github.io/leonardblog/2021/01/14/Filling%20the%20void</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leonardmutambanengwe.github.io/leonardblog/2021/01/14/Filling-the-void.html">&lt;p&gt;Looking out of the window, on a moody January morning, it is hard to tell how I got here. It is 2021, and it seems the hopes for a better 2021 have not started to bear fruit, with the pandemic raging more than ever, outisde in the world. Infections and deaths are up, many countries hitting record highs, eclipsing the first wave figures. But life has to go on. We live day by day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been a good 2+ years since I have written anything, and this post, as titled, is to fill that gap and give a perspective on the road ahead. I guess it also refers to the perspective itself. I feel this an effort to rise to some occassion, and that I can only do by admitting that I had lost my way, somewhere along the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember, 2018 felt great. Completed my qualification, spoke at my first conference, constituted &lt;a href=&quot;https://zimbabwedata.science&quot;&gt;Data Science Zimbabwe&lt;/a&gt; and we had our first meet up and I was looking forward to taking my first real venture, Peachgrove, an horticultural produce and marketing venture, off the ground. Everything felt good. The sky was the limit. But Zimbabwe is not an easy country, and the hope of the reset in 2017 (despite the same honchos still running the country) faded and all illusions disappeared quite fast. Having to build up and get things running in a volatile environment meant the horticultural venture would really not translate to anything except lessons. Lessons that will be valuable in anything I attempt going forward and still one day, I certainly hope to explore the venture, to start again, for I feel it is a part of my being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along the road, another venture came up. Quantum Analytica, a data analytics-marketing-systems development outfit. The prospects looked great. We had initial contact with multiple clients, the appetite for our services seemed bottomless. The discussions were amazing, the founding team even more so. But maybe because I was still holding on to Peachgrove, hoping that I can find a way out of the malaise it was suffering, and Quantum Analytica seemed to be able to play a role in that. But it also fell apart. The environment in Zimbabwe has impacted a lot of things for entrepreneurs. The volatility impacting the effectiveness of any resources, but nothing is more poignant than the impact on the people resources. It becomes to hard to get people to buy in into any entrepreneurial venture. It definitely is not unexpected given the situation. It still makes it hard. And so we found ourselves having to shelf a good opportunity. And I went back to farming…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the while, Data Science Zimbabwe has been chugging along, quietly in the background. DSZ was created as a means to provide a platform to bring together Zimbabweans interested in data and data-based solutions together. And we managed to get the interest going in a short time. I am so grateful to the community for making up a vibrant community. Operating on a zero revenue budget, there has been more done within the organization that I could have thought in 2018, beginning the journey. And it has been my ray of hope, as everything else seemed untenable, the prospect of making an impact is very humbling and satisfying. And even in 2020 when the pandemic threatened everything else, the community kept on, engaging over Whatsapp, participating in hackathons, and I can definitely say for the near future, it is my main consideration and I hope 2021 sees the community grow in leaps and bounds, and initiatives lead to visibility for the community at the forefront of the 4th Industrial Revolution in Zimbabwe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So 2021 is here. And the hope is that for the lessons learnt in the past 2 years, and the new normal that is being hashed out by the pandemic, resilience and taking care of opportunities that present themselves are the order of the day to fill that void and get back to the unfettered hope that coursed these veins in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s go!!!! I am up for it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Looking out of the window, on a moody January morning, it is hard to tell how I got here. It is 2021, and it seems the hopes for a better 2021 have not started to bear fruit, with the pandemic raging more than ever, outisde in the world. Infections and deaths are up, many countries hitting record highs, eclipsing the first wave figures. But life has to go on. We live day by day.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Back to Africa ..and of conferences and travel documents</title><link href="https://leonardmutambanengwe.github.io/leonardblog/2018/09/14/Back-to-Africa-/and-of-conferences-and-travel-documents.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Back to Africa ..and of conferences and travel documents" /><published>2018-09-14T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-09-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://leonardmutambanengwe.github.io/leonardblog/2018/09/14/Back-to-Africa-/Back%20to%20Africa%20..and%20of%20conferences%20and%20travel%20documents</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leonardmutambanengwe.github.io/leonardblog/2018/09/14/Back-to-Africa-/and-of-conferences-and-travel-documents.html">&lt;p&gt;So I have been back from Italy for close to 75 days now, and it has mostly been chilling, watching television and catching up with family. I have also put in a number of applications with some local companies for data science jobs and had a grand total of ZERO responses. My closest bet at the moment is a company that does not know whether to put me under IT or Finance departments. But that is the situation in South Africa currently, with the onset of economic problems and perennial youth unemployment. Worse still, I am Zimbabwean in South Africa, job issues are always to be expected. So what to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2018 I, with others, started a group called Data Science Zimbabwe that we hope can be a platform for people in data-related professions and academia to lead the 4th Industrial Revolution in Zimbabwe. We have only so far communicated via WhatsApp, but I am hopeful of the prospects. I am hoping we can have our first meet-up soon and start putting together a solid foundation for the advancement of data science and machine and deep learning as well as Artificial Intelligence in Zimbabwe. So for the time being, that is what my data science path has led me to and I am relishing the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also done a talk proposal for PyCon Zimbabwe on Agent-based modeling and Network Analysis using MESA and NetworkX, hopefully the experience is positive and provides an opportunity to make Data Science Zimbabwe visible within the tech community. This leads me to an important topic, that impacted me personally and have seen general discussions about on social media as well, globally. The choice of venues for conferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Deep Learning Indaba was set for Stellenbosch University in South Africa. This is an important conference, in terms of my field and is important that participation, especially from Africans, show that the field is alive and kicking on the continent. However, South Africa is one of the hardest countries to get immigration documents for on the continent, especially to fellow Africans. I know the topic of holding conferences in countries that are inclusive is not new, and has gained traction in light of the trends in geopolitics in Europe and America. And here in Africa it is of no less concern. I was heartbroken when I saw a tweet about someone who had been given the whole funding to attend the conference, on condition they got their documents for travel to South Africa sorted out. No prize for guessing the outcome of their application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is Africa ready for full on co-operation in cutting edge fields that transcends borders? Can we get the academics, practitioners, experts etc in the same room, without hassle about movement from country A to country B? Should these types of conferences, be it in our field or any other, be held in countries that make it hard for those from other countries to travel there and be a part of these important get-togethers. These are the kind of matters that will affect Africa’s ability to embrace advancements in any area and be able to build lasting solutions to problems on our continent. I feel sorry for anyone who would have wanted to attend this conference and has to live with Twitter updates and Github practicals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rwanda has done Africa a solid with their changes to requirements for travel to the country, for Africans. This is a move to be applauded. But at this moment, I would tip my hat to any country on the continent that will suspend its (obviously) rigid, red tape surrounding movement for academic or professional conferences and gatherings and get-togethers, because if Africa is going to progress, we need to have great minds together as frequently as possible. This will help create networks all over the continent, not hindered by the travel requirements and a solid hope for the getting a lot of work done and catching up to global levels of progress in many fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope one day Africa will not let colonial demarcations hamper the progress of its people, and we will see the free flow of knowledge from Cape to Cairo.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">So I have been back from Italy for close to 75 days now, and it has mostly been chilling, watching television and catching up with family. I have also put in a number of applications with some local companies for data science jobs and had a grand total of ZERO responses. My closest bet at the moment is a company that does not know whether to put me under IT or Finance departments. But that is the situation in South Africa currently, with the onset of economic problems and perennial youth unemployment. Worse still, I am Zimbabwean in South Africa, job issues are always to be expected. So what to do?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome!</title><link href="https://leonardmutambanengwe.github.io/leonardblog/markdown/2018/06/21/Welcome.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome!" /><published>2018-06-21T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-06-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://leonardmutambanengwe.github.io/leonardblog/markdown/2018/06/21/Welcome</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leonardmutambanengwe.github.io/leonardblog/markdown/2018/06/21/Welcome.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a log of activities and expected for the year commencing from my return to the Motherland. I hope I can look at it in one year and make an informed decision about the next steps I want to take. It will also have, general blog posts, on matters of interest, especially techpreneurship and general economics commentary. So here is to inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="markdown" /><summary type="html">This is a log of activities and expected for the year commencing from my return to the Motherland. I hope I can look at it in one year and make an informed decision about the next steps I want to take. It will also have, general blog posts, on matters of interest, especially techpreneurship and general economics commentary. So here is to inspiration.</summary></entry></feed>